<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-08-22T10:35:31+02:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">IN2040 FP</title><subtitle>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.</subtitle><author><name> </name></author><entry><title type="html">Welcome to Functional programming (IN2040), autumn 2025</title><link href="/functionalprogramming/2025/05/01/fpwelcome-2025.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to Functional programming (IN2040), autumn 2025" /><published>2025-05-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2025-05-01T08:11:00+02:00</updated><id>/functionalprogramming/2025/05/01/fpwelcome-2025</id><content type="html" xml:base="/functionalprogramming/2025/05/01/fpwelcome-2025.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="about-this-semester">About this semester</h1>

<h3 id="lectures">Lectures</h3>

<p>Corona is a thing of the dim pasts and lectures will be held the way it used to be, in the lecture hall (Simula@OJD).</p>

<h3 id="youtube">Youtube</h3>

<p>One perhaps positive effect of the virus times was that many lectures produced video-ed versions of the presentations, like screencasts or recorded lectures. This lecture as well. We will not make a new version of the videos, there is no reason for doing that (and lot of effort went into it), but we will link in the versions produced mostly 2020, uploaded at youtube.</p>

<h3 id="language">Language</h3>

<p>The lecture will be given in Norwegian. It is actually my first lecture ever given in Norwegian (but now for the forth time), so maybe my Norwegian improved. In these (inofficial) pages, however, I’ll write in English, it takes too much time otherwise.</p>

<h2 id="exercises-and-group-work">Exercises and group work</h2>

<p>The videos are fine as supplementary information and electronic format. Though reading the book and in particular doing the exercises and obligs is central for mastering the material. I like to compare that with learning how to play the guitar. No particular reason for exactly choosing guitars as comparison, except that since some time I try to learn doing that. Of course one can watch and listen to Eric Clapton, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RmdRCywCtbs">Andrés Segovia</a>, or Eddie van Halen on youtube (or whatever your top guitar hero might be), maybe watching the close-ups of the finger plays, or listening to some guitar teacher. All that may be instructive, it may help to correct the way you hold your guitar or place and move your fingers, or you may see new techniques, and it sure can be inspiring and motivating, to see and listen to some master or instructor.</p>

<p>Seeing enough youtube and reading enough material, one may be able to convincingly talk about what’s important when playing a guitar, describe techniques, using terminology like a pro (finger picking, leganto, arpeggio, whatever). But a talk about how to play guitar is not a live gig. So <strong>unless one strums the six strings with one’s own fingers</strong>, starting with simple chords, and gradually advancing the level of difficulty, <strong>one will never get far</strong>.</p>

<p>Same here: talking about programs like a pro (tail-recursion, applicative order, higher-order functions, stream-programming, to mention a few topics covered by the lecture…) is not the same as programming. So, doing exercises is important!</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Learning is not the product of teaching. Learning is the product of the activity of learners. (John Holt)</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name> </name></author><category term="functionalprogramming" /><category term="functional programming" /><category term="IN2040" /><category term="scheme" /><category term="lisp" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry></feed>